Toni Morrison Papers, 1917-2015: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Toni Morrison Papers
1970-2015
1917-2015
C1491
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
200.43 linear feet
Morrison, Toni. 1931-
Toni Morrison (born Chloe Ardelia Wofford, 1931) is a Nobel prize-winning American author, editor, and Professor Emeritus at Princeton University. The material described in this finding aid consists of manuscripts, drafts, galleys, and proofs of Morrison's novels; personal correspondence; editorial files relating to Morrison's work at Random House and later publication of two posthumous works by Toni Cade Bambara; and academic and teaching files, particularly pertaining to SUNY Albany and Princeton University. Other material from the collection, including drafts of non-fiction, theatrical, and children's literature, office working files, published books, press clippings, photographs, audiovisual materials, awards and memorabilia will be added as processing is completed.
Toni Morrison was born Chloe Ardelia Wofford in Lorain, Ohio in 1931. She attended Howard University, graduating in 1953 with a degree in English, then received an MA in literature from Cornell University in 1955.
After a brief teaching stint at Texas Southern University, Morrison returned to teach at Howard in 1957. There, she married architect Harold Morrison, with whom she had two sons, Harold Ford Morrison (born 1961) and Slade Kevin Morrison (1964-2010). The two divorced around the time of Slade’s birth, after which Morrison began working as a textbook editor for a division of Random House based in Syracuse, NY. In 1967, Morrison was promoted to senior editor and moved to New York City, where she worked with a number of emerging influential African-American writers, including Toni Cade Bambara, Angela Davis, Henry Dumas, and Gayl Jones, in addition to editing The Black Book (1974), a compilation of African-American historical documents.
Morrison’s first novel, The Bluest Eye, was published in 1970. She has published a total of eleven novels to date, winning numerous literary and cultural awards including the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction for Beloved in 1988, the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1993, the National Humanities Medal in 2000, and the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2012. In addition to her novels, Morrison has written non-fiction, poetry, children’s literature (in collaboration with her son Slade), and dramatic works.
In 1983, she left her position at Random House to concentrate on writing and teaching, serving as the Albert Schweitzer Professor of the Humanities at SUNY Albany from 1984-1989, then the Robert E. Goheen Professor in the Council of the Humanities at Princeton University until her retirement in 2006. During this time, she taught classes in creative writing, African-American studies, and, at Princeton, developed the interdisciplinary Atelier program. She has also served as a visiting professor and lecturer at numerous institutions, including Yale University, the University of Michigan, the University of Chicago, and Harvard University.
Morrison currently resides in the Hudson Valley of New York State.
The material described in this finding aid consists of manuscripts, drafts, galleys, and proofs of Morrison's novels; personal correspondence; editorial files relating to Morrison's work at Random House and later publication of two posthumous works by Toni Cade Bambara; and academic and teaching files, particularly pertaining to SUNY Albany and Princeton University. Other material from the collection, including drafts of non-fiction, theatrical, and children's literature, office working files, published books, press clippings, photographs, audiovisual materials, awards and memorabilia will be added as processing is completed.
The collection is arranged into the following series:
The collection is open for research. Toni Morrison's manuscript material, including drafts, typescripts, galleys, and proofs found in boxes 1-11; 13-19; 22-29; 32-47; 50-56; 59-62; and 64-66 are available only via digital access in the reading room.
Some of this material is stored off site. Please allow 24-48 hrs for retrieval.
Some material in this collection, particularly found in Series 1: Writings and Series 2: Correspondence, was damaged by the fire that destroyed Morrison's upstate New York home in 1993. Damage ranges from charred edges to pages missing significant portions or rendered illegible.
2009 (AM 2015-62). 2015 accruals: (AM 2015-74), (AM 2015-89), (AM 2015-98).
Nothing was removed from the collection during 2015-2016 processing.
Other materials relating to Toni Morrison's work at Random House may be found in the Random House records at Columbia University's Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Morrison, Toni.; African American authors -- 20th century -- Sources.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Sources.; Novelists.; Nobel Prize winners.; Women Nobel Prize winners.; Correspondence.; Fan mail.; Interviews.; Proofs (printed matter).; Typescripts.; American literature; Literature
- Series 1: Writings, 1917-2015; 66 boxes
  This series is arranged into subseries by genre. Currently, all material relating to Morrison's novels are available; other subseries relating to her non-fiction, children's literature, dramatic works, and other writings will be added as they are processed.
  Consists of research material, notes, outlines, drafts, galleys, and proofs. Yellow legal notepads contain notes, early draft material, and inserts for later typed and printed versions. Notepads are identified by their first lines, though a single notepad may contain a variety of material, including material relating to other works, correspondence drafts, and other unrelated notes. Corrected typescript and printout drafts often show significant revisions. Material from various stages of the publication process is present, including setting copies with copy-editor's and typesetter's marks, galleys, page proofs, F&Gs (folded-and-gathered pages, in signatures but not yet bound), blueline proofs ("confirmation blues"), advance copies (bound uncorrected proofs, pre-publication, often used for book reviewers) and production/design material with page and dust-jacket samples. Page numbers are noted for paginated material
  - Subseries 1A: Novels, 1917-2015; 1970-2015; 66 boxes
    Arranged chronologically by publication date.
    All of Morrison's novels except Song of Solomon are represented (this material was likely destroyed in the 1993 fire).
    - The Bluest Eye, 1970; 2 boxes
      For the short story "Two of Eves," an early version of The Bluest Eye, see Subseries 2: Short Fiction.
      - Outlines and Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Toni Morrison has required the Library to make surrogate copies of all of her manuscripts (including typescripts and proofs) and diaries (appointment books), including but not restricted to those damaged by fire in 1993. This is for conservation reasons, to prevent damage and deterioration by repeated use. Researchers are required to use digital surrogates in the reading room of the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
      - "The Bluest Eye: On the southeast corner...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "II. It would be inaccurate...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "III. 3. This was at least the fifth time...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Notes for The Bluest Eye/Part IV Social worker: and Eunice", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "At one time people only saw slow footed teenage boys...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Att: To Him Who Greatly Ennobled Human Nature...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Where's the mirror again?", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Cholly and the Block Boys...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Soaphead Church", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "1. Rosemary Magazini is our friend...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "We--Frieda And Me--Meet Eunice", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "It was autumn when Mr. Shelby came...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "'Let's do something' Frieda said.", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "1. More on house: and life in it...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "We dropped our seeds...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "A Play", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - The Bluest Eye Draft Fragments, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - The Bluest Eye Drafts, undated; portions of 2 boxes
        - The Bluest Eye Draft, undated; Typescript (original and photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - The Bluest Eye Draft, undated; Typescript (photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - The Bluest Eye Draft, undated; Typescript (photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - The Bluest Eye Draft, undated; Typescript (original and photocopy), corrected. 1 item
          - The Bluest Eye Draft Pages 1-133, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
          - The Bluest Eye Draft Pages 134-[199], undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - The Bluest Eye Draft, undated; Typescript (original and photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - The Bluest Eye Galley Proofs, 1970; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Sula, 1973; 3 boxes
      - Sula Draft Fragment, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 3, Folder 1)
        1 p.
      - Sula Draft, 1973; Typescript, corrected (photocopy). 1 item (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Pages 1-215.
      - Sula Setting Copy, 1973; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Pages i-214 (stamped 1-223), with missing pages.
      - Sula Confirmation Blues, 1973; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Pages 1-174. With publisher's cover letter, dated October 9, 1973.
      - Sula Galley Proofs, 1973; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Sula Galley Proofs: Marked Set, 1973; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Tar Baby, 1981-1983; 6 boxes
      - Notes, undated; Typescript. 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
        Page 14.
      - Tar Baby Drafts, undated; 3 boxes (2 partial)
        - Tar Baby Draft, undated; Typescript (photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
        - Tar Baby Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
          Pages 1-361, with missing pages.
        - Tar Baby Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item
          Pages 1-332.
          - Tar Baby Draft Pages 1-261, undated; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
          - Tar Baby Draft Pages 262-[332], undated; 1 item (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Tar Baby Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
          Pages 1-406.
        - Tar Baby Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 8, Folder 4)
          Page 233-400.
      - Tar Baby Advance Copy, 1981; 1 item (Box 8, Folder 5)
        Pages 1-[306].
      - Tar Baby Galley Proofs, 1981; 1 item (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Tar Baby Screenplay Drafts, 1983; 2 boxes
        - Tar Baby Screenplay Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 10, Folder 1)
          Pages 2-20.
        - Tar Baby Screenplay Draft, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 10, Folder 2)
          Pages 87-187.
        - Tar Baby Screenplay Draft, 1983; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
          Pages 1-224.
        - Tar Baby Screenplay Draft, undated; Typescript. 1 item (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
          Pages 1-145.
    - Beloved, 1984 September 21-1999; 8 boxes
      Numbered drafts per original folder labels.
      - Beloved Research Files, 1985-1986; more than 13 folders
        Consists of research notes and photocopies of articles, book excerpts, and primary sources.
        - 19th Century Legislation Regarding Slaves, 1985 March; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 1)
        - Atlanta Historical Society, undated; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 2)
        - Bibliographies, undated; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 3)
        - Blacks in Circuses, Slideshows, etc., 1985 April; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 4)
        - Cincinnati (19th Century), 1985 March; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
        - Database, 1985 March 27; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Kentucky (19th Century), undated; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 7)
        - Kentucky State Historical Society, undated; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - Middle Passage, 1985-1986; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Research Findings (Copies), 1985; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 10)
        - Slave Narratives, undated; 2 folders (Box 12, Folder 11)
        - Smith, James McCune, 1985 February; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 12)
        - Sojourner Truth, 1985 February; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Writing Schedule, undated; Typescript. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - House Sketch, undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Family Tree, undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Calendar, undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Outlines and Notes, undated; Typescript, corrected. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - "Hi Man had said...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - "TR to Stamp Paid", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "After the ice skating", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - "Her father's daughter...", undated; Notepad. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - "Denver who knew all about silence...", undated; Notepad. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - "Some thoughts", undated; Notepad. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - "Curtains--light--humming", undated; Notepad. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - "6. JFK...", undated; Notepad. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - "I don't have to explain...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - "124 was loud...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - "Denver comes out...", undated; Notepad pages. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Beloved Draft Fragments, undated; Typescript and printout, corrected. 2 folders (Box 13, Folder 17-18)
      - Beloved Synopsis and Early Draft, undated; Typescript. 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 19)
        Pages 1-7, 1-6.
      - Beloved Drafts, circa 1984-1987; 5 boxes (2 partial)
        - Beloved Draft 1, undated; Typescript and printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 13, Folder 20)
        - Beloved Draft 2, undated; Printout, corrected (photocopy). 1 item (Box 13, Folder 21)
        - Beloved Draft 3, 1984 September 21; Printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 14, Folder 1)
          Pages 1-189. With note from Mary Maguire.
        - Beloved Draft, circa 1984-1987; Printout (photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
          Pages 1-394.
        - Beloved Draft 6, circa 1984-1987; Printout (photocopy), corrected. 1 item (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
          Pages 1-394. Robert Gottlieb's copy.
        - Beloved Draft, circa 1984-1987; Printout. 1 item
          Pages 1-517.
          - Beloved Draft Pages 1-400, circa 1984-1987; 4 folders (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
          - Beloved Draft Pages 401-517, circa 1984-1987; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 1)
        - Beloved Draft, circa 1984-1987; Printout, corrected. 1 item
          - Beloved Draft Part 1, circa 1984-1987; 3 folders (Box 16, Folder 2-4)
          - Beloved Draft Part 2, circa 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
      - Beloved Setting Copy, 1987; Printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
        Pages 1-541.
      - Beloved Author's Set Rough Pages, 1987; 1 item (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
        Pages [i-vi], 3-277.
      - Beloved Master Page Proofs, 1987; 1 item (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
        Pages i-vii, 1-277.
      - Beloved First Pass Master Rough Pages, 1987; 1 item (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
        Pages i- vii, 1 (formerly 3)-277.
      - Beloved Cut Page Proofs, 1987; 1 item
        - Beloved Cut Page Proof Pages 1-194, 1987; 1 item (Box 18, Folder 7)
        - Beloved Cut Page Proof Pages 195-277, 1987; 1 item (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Beloved First Pass Author's Set Proofs for Reprint, 1998 June 22; 1 item (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
        Pages a-b, i-viii, 1-326.
      - Beloved Second Pass Proofs for Reprint, 1998 July 20; 1 item (Box 19, Folder 4-5)
        Pages a-b, i-viii, 1-326. With publisher's memo dated July 20,1998.
      - Beloved Third Pass Proofs for Reprint, 1999; 1 item (Box 19, Folder 6)
        Pages i-x, 1-290. With memo with proofreader's query dated April 27, 1999 and letter from Lori Lipsky, Publisher at Dutton Plume, dated April 28,1999.
    - Jazz, 1917-1992; 1989-1992; 10 boxes
      - Jazz Research Files, 1917-1992; 2 boxes
        - 1990 Research Assistant Notes, 1989-1990; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - "African-American Properties Recognized in the National Register of Historic Places", undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Anderson, Jervis: This Was Harlem: A Cultural Portrait 1900-1950, undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Andrews, Charles: "A History of the NY African Free Schools, 1787 to Present" (1830), 1960; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 4)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, originally published in 1830, reprinted 1960 by Negro Universities Press.
        - Background Notes and Photocopies, undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 5)
        - "Blacks in Pennsylvania History" Afro-American Historical & Cultural Museum, Philadelphia, 1988; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - Bontemps, Anna: The Harlem Renaissance Remembered, undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - Bulletin of NY Public Library "Ethiopia Unshackled", 1987; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 8)
          Photocopied journal article published April 1965, with letter from research assistant Elizabeth Adams to the New York Historical Society, dated December 22, 1987.
        - Correspondence Related to Next Publication, 1987 December-1988 February; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 9)
        - Dixon, Robert: "The Education of the Negro in NYC 1853-1900", undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 10)
        - Fox, Ted: Showtime at the Apollo, "Harlem's Early Years--The Apollo's Heritage", undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 11)
        - Franklin, Vincent: "The Education of Black Philadelphia, 1900-1950", 1979; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 12)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, published by the University of Pennsylvania Press.
        - Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1988; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 13)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, originally published in 1868 by the Government Printing Office.
        - History of Schools for the Colored Population, 1969; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 14)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, published by Arno Press and the New York Times.
        - Huggins, Nathan: Harlem Renaissance, 1971; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 15)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, published by Oxford University Press.
        - Jones, Norrence: "Masters, Slaves, and Those Between: Controls and Controllers in Antebellum South Carolina", 1987; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 16)
        - Lewis, David Levering: When Harlem was in Vogue, 1981; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 17)
          Photocopied excerpt of book published by Knopf.
        - Mabee, Carleton: "Black Education in NY State: From Colonial to Modern Times", 1979; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 18)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, published by Syracuse University Press, 1979.
        - McPherson, James M. "The Abolitionist Legacy: From Reconstruction to the NAACP", undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 19)
        - Ment, David: "Patterns of Public School Segregation, 1900-1940: Comparison of NYC, New Rochelle, & New Haven", undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 20)
        - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 21)
        - Negro Education: A Study of the Private and Higher Schools for Colored People in the US, 1969; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 22)
          Photocopied excerpt of book, published by Arno Press and New York Times.
        - The New York Age, 1917-1926; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 23)
          Photocopied newspaper pages.
        - The New York Amsterdam News, 1926; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 24)
          Photocopied newspaper pages of newspapers.
        - Opportunity: "Negro Migration in NY State" & Misc. Other Articles, 1926; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 1)
          Photocopied pages of newspapers.
        - Opportunity: A Journal of Negro Life, 1926; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 2)
        - Opportunity: A Journal of Negro Life, 1929 September; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 3)
        - Osofsky, Gilbert: Harlem: The Making of a Ghetto Negro New York 1890-1930, 1966; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 4)
          Photocopied excerpt of book published by Harper & Row.
        - The Quaker Collection, Haverford College, undated; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 5)
        - Research Materials, undated; 2 folders (Box 21, Folder 6-7)
        - Research for Sequel to Beloved, 1987-1988; 3 folders (Box 21, Folder 8-10)
        - Schiffman, Jack: Harlem Heyday: A Pictoral History of Black Show Business and the Apollo, undated; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 11)
        - "Sugar Hill: A Citadel of Styles and Echoes of an Earlier America", 1987; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 12)
        - Survey Magazine, 1987; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 13)
          Photocopied pages of magazine published 1925, with note from Siena College librarian dated October 30, 1987.
        - Thompson, Marion: "The Education of Negroes in New Jersey" (1971), 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 14)
          Photocopied excerpt of book published by Arno Press and New York Times, 1971.
        - Walker, Sheila: "The Feast of Good Death: An Afro-Catholic Emancipation Celebration in Brazil", 1992; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 15)
          Photocopied article published in SAGE, Fall 1986; faxed by Paula Giddings, January 17, 1992.
        - The Weeksville Society, 1988; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 16)
        - Work, Monroe: "A Bibliography of the Negro in Africa & America", 1965; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 17)
          Photocopied excerpt of book published by Argosy-Antiquarian Inc.
      - Notes, 1989; Autograph, typescript, and printouts, corrected. 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Jazz Mss/Yellows, undated; Notepads. 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous, undated; Autograph, typescript, and printouts, corrected. 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Chapter 1, circa 1989-1992; 2 folders
        - Annotated Folder, circa 1989-1992; 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - "How does a book sound...", circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Pages 1-4.
        - Jvoice1, circa 1989-1992; Printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - "and half civilian...", circa 1989-1992; Printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Pages 2-4.
        - "Swanning--trying to capture the talking/book voice", circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          6 pp.
        - Jazznote, circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Pages 1-2.
        - "Putting her hand to something...", circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - "She went on like that...", circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Pages 2-3.
        - Violet, circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Pages 1-3.
        - Violet Revised, circa 1989-1992; Printout. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - Violet Revised, circa 1989-1992; Printout, corrected. 1 item (Box 22, Folder 4)